nginx JS — Dynamic Reconfiguration Guide (for single worker)

│ DRAFT FOR COMMENTS — This document is a work in progress. Content, API names, and examples are subject to change before release.

Overview

The nginx JS DOM lets you read and write live nginx configuration from JavaScript running inside nginx workers. This guide covers the write-side of that API:

•

write_mode / read_mode — control where property assignments go and where reads come from (global shared struct vs per-request snapshot).

•

snapshot() / restore() — capture a point-in-time copy of a COM sub-tree and roll it back at any moment.

Together these two mechanisms let you implement safe hot-reload, per-tenant routing, A/B configuration experiments, and rollback-on-error patterns without reloading nginx.

Terminology

Term │ Meaning

global struct │ The C struct shared by all workers that was set up at config parse time. Mutations here affect every new request immediately.

per-request snapshot │ A shallow copy of r→loc_conf[] (pointer array) plus deep copies of whatever individual C structs have been mutated for this request. Exists only for the duration of one request.

COM node │ A JavaScript wrapper object (NginxLocation, NginxProxy, NginxPeer, NginxRRPeer, NginxUpstream, …) backed by a nginx C struct.

write_mode and read_mode

Default behaviour

Both write_mode and read_mode default to 'global'.

loc.handler = (req) => {
// By default all writes go to the global shared struct
req.location.root = '/new/root'; // immediately visible to ALL requests
};

write_mode = 'global' (default)
Request N Global struct
────────── ─────────────
req.location ──────────────────► clcf { root = '/new/root', ... }
.root = '/new' │
│ visible to Request N+1
▼
Request N+1 Global struct
────────── ─────────────
req.location ──────────────────► clcf { root = '/new/root', ... }

write_mode values

Value │ Constant │ Meaning

'global' │ NGX_JS_WRITE_GLOBAL (0x01) │ All property assignments write to the global shared C struct only. No per-request snapshot is created. Default.

'local' │ NGX_JS_WRITE_LOCAL (0x02) │ Writes go to a per-request snapshot copy only. A snapshot is created automatically on the first write. The global struct is never touched. Other concurrent requests see the original global values.

'both' │ NGX_JS_WRITE_BOTH (0x03) │ Writes go to both the global struct and the per-request snapshot. Semantics of 'global' for other requests, semantics of 'local' for the current request.

read_mode values

Value │ Meaning

'global' │ Property reads always return the value from the global shared struct. Default.

'local' │ Property reads prefer the per-request snapshot when one exists, falling back to the global struct automatically (because r→loc_conf[idx] == op→clcf until a snapshot is taken).

API

req.location.setWriteMode(mode) // 'global' | 'local' | 'both'
req.location.setReadMode(mode) // 'global' | 'local'

Both methods update the opaque state of the NginxLocation wrapper and propagate the new write_mode into the per-request context (rctx) so that sub-object setters (proxy, gzip, headers, rewrite) also honour it.

Flow diagram: write_mode interactions

┌──────────────────────┐
│ Request N starts │
│ write_mode='global' │ ← default
└──────────┬───────────┘
│
┌────────────────────┼────────────────────┐
│ │ │
write_mode='global' write_mode='local' write_mode='both'
│ │ │
▼ ▼ ▼
┌──────────────┐ ┌──────────────────┐ ┌──────────────────┐
│ Global clcf │ │ ensure_snapshot()│ │ ensure_snapshot()│
│ (shared by │ │ per-req copy │ │ per-req copy │
│ all reqs) │ │ written ONLY │ │ written │
└──────┬───────┘ └──────────────────┘ │+ │
│ │ Global clcf │
│ other requests see │ also written │
│ the new value immediately └──────────────────┘
▼
Request N+1 reads the
mutated global value

Example: per-tenant root directory

loc.handler = (req) => {
// Isolate writes to this request — global is never touched
req.location.setWriteMode('local');
req.location.setReadMode('local');
const tenant = req.getVar('http_x_tenant') || 'default';
req.location.root = '/var/www/' + tenant;
// req.sendfile still works with the local root
req.sendfile('/index.html');
};

Other concurrent requests continue to read the original global root because this request only wrote to its per-request snapshot.

Example: persistent global mutation (hot reload)

// Endpoint that updates the upstream peer weight globally
nginx.http.servers.forEach(srv => {
const loc = srv.locations.find(l => l.path === '/admin/set-weight');
if (!loc) { return; }
loc.handler = (req) => {
// Default write_mode='global' — affects all future requests
const body = JSON.parse(req.body);
const ups = nginx.http.upstreams.find(u => u.name === body.upstream);
if (!ups) { req.respond(404, {}, 'upstream not found'); return; }
const peer = ups.peers.find(p => p.address === body.peer);
if (!peer) { req.respond(404, {}, 'peer not found'); return; }
peer.weight = body.weight;
req.json({ applied: true });
};
});

suspendAcceptance() and resumeAcceptance()

Purpose

JavaScript within a worker is single-threaded, but nginx is event-driven: the event loop may dispatch a second request between any two consecutive assignments in a handler. Without suspension a concurrent request on this worker could observe a half-updated config:

req.location.root = '/new'; // ← request B starts here ...
req.location.proxy.readTimeout = 5000; // ... and misses this write

nginx.suspendAcceptance() removes all listening socket read events from this worker’s event loop. No new requests are dispatched by this worker while acceptance is suspended; incoming TCP connections queue harmlessly in the OS socket backlog (up to net.core.somaxconn). Other workers continue accepting normally.

Call nginx.resumeAcceptance() once the batch is complete.

: Both functions are synchronous and return undefined. They are only callable from a worker process — not from config phase, and not from a Worker or SharedWorker thread.

For changes that must be consistent across all workers, use nginx.suspendAllWorkers() / nginx.resumeAllWorkers() instead — see the for all workers guide.

Example: atomic batch config update

loc.handler = async (req) => {
const cfg = JSON.parse(await req.readBody());
nginx.suspendAcceptance(); // no new requests on this worker
req.location.root = cfg.root;
req.location.gzip.level = cfg.gzip.level;
req.location.proxy.readTimeout = cfg.proxy.readTimeout;
req.location.proxy.connectTimeout = cfg.proxy.connectTimeout;
nginx.resumeAcceptance(); // restore normal accept behaviour
req.json({ applied: true });
};

Example: atomic batch with rollback

Always call resumeAcceptance() even when an exception is thrown. The try/finally pattern guarantees this:

loc.handler = async (req) => {
const snap = req.location.snapshot(); // save rollback point
nginx.suspendAcceptance();
try {
const cfg = JSON.parse(await req.readBody());
req.location.root = cfg.root;
req.location.proxy.readTimeout = cfg.proxy.readTimeout;
req.location.gzip.level = cfg.gzip.level;
req.json({ applied: true });
} catch (e) {
snap.restore(); // revert partial mutations
req.respond(500, {}, e.message);
} finally {
nginx.resumeAcceptance(); // always re-enable
}
};

: Do not perform async I/O (network probes, nginx.setTimeout) inside the suspension window. Awaiting I/O while suspended keeps this worker stopped — it cannot drain its timer queue or respond to existing keep-alive requests. Validate config before calling suspendAcceptance(), then execute only synchronous writes inside the window.

Flow diagram

Request handler: Event loop (this worker):
nginx.suspendAcceptance()
│ removes listen read events ───────────────────────────────►
│ no new connections accepted
│ existing requests may complete
│
req.location.root = '/a' (no interleaving possible here)
req.location.gzip.level = 3
req.location.proxy.readTimeout = 5000
│
nginx.resumeAcceptance()
│ re-adds listen read events ───────────────────────────────►
queued connections accepted

snapshot() and restore()

What snapshot() captures

obj.snapshot() reads the current visible values of all settable properties on obj (through read_mode) and stores them in a NginxSnapshot handle. For NginxLocation it also recursively captures the settable fields of sub-objects (proxy, gzip, headers, rewrite).

COM class │ Fields captured by snapshot()

NginxLocation │ root, handler, sendfile, tcpNopush, tcpNodelay, etag, keepaliveTimeout, keepaliveRequests, clientMaxBodySize, clientBodyTimeout, sendTimeout, defaultType, alias, satisfy, limitExcept, lingering, lingeringTimeout, lingeringTime, resolverTimeout, chunkedTransferEncoding, msieRefresh, logNotFound, logSubrequest, recursiveErrorPages, clientBodyBufferSize, clientBodyInFileOnly, clientBodyInSingleBuffer, resetTimedoutConnection, absoluteRedirect, serverNameInRedirect, portInRedirect, msiePadding, ifModifiedSince, maxRanges, authDelay, keepaliveTime, sendLowat, postponeOutput, keepaliveDisable, keepaliveMinTimeout, sendfileMaxChunk, readAhead, directio, directioAlignment, errorPage

NginxLocation (sub: proxy) │ httpVersion, connectTimeout, sendTimeout, readTimeout, buffering, requestBuffering, interceptErrors, bufferSize, nextUpstreamTries, nextUpstreamTimeout

NginxLocation (sub: gzip) │ enable, level, minLength, vary

NginxLocation (sub: headers) │ headersInherit, trailersInherit

NginxLocation (sub: rewrite) │ log, uninitializedVariableWarn, stackSize

NginxPeer / NginxRRPeer │ weight, maxFails, down, failTimeout, maxConns

NginxUpstream │ All current peers (one sub-node per peer, each with the fields above)

Null/undefined getter results are silently skipped (e.g. alias on a root-based location returns null and is not stored).

What restore() does

snap.restore() iterates all stored nodes and calls the standard property setter for each captured value using JS_SetPropertyStr.

The setter path handles:

•

write_mode routing (global / local / both).

•

ngx_js_ensure_core_snapshot() / ngx_js_ensure_module_snapshot() — creating per-request snapshot copies when needed.

•

Lock acquisition for NginxRRPeer properties.

restore() is best-effort: individual setter errors are silently cleared so that one failed field does not prevent others from being restored.

restore() is idempotent: you can call it multiple times safely.

restore() mode override

snap.restore() // use current write_mode (default)
snap.restore({ mode: 'global' }) // force all writes to global struct
snap.restore({ mode: 'local' }) // force all writes to per-req snapshot
snap.restore({ mode: 'both' }) // write to both

The override temporarily sets loc_op→write_mode and rctx→write_mode for the duration of the restore call, then restores the original values.

Interaction table: snapshot × write_mode

Scenario | snapshot captures | restore() writes to
───────────────────────────┼───────────────────┼─────────────────────
write_mode='global' │ current global │ global
default, no override │ values │ (other reqs see it)
───────────────────────────┼───────────────────┼─────────────────────
write_mode='local' │ current local │ local snapshot only
no override │ (= global if no │ (global untouched)
│ prior mutation) │
───────────────────────────┼───────────────────┼─────────────────────
write_mode='both' │ current local │ both global and
no override │ (mirrors global) │ local snapshot
───────────────────────────┼───────────────────┼─────────────────────
Any write_mode + │ whatever │ forced global
restore({mode:'global'}) │ read_mode says │
───────────────────────────┼───────────────────┼─────────────────────
write_mode='local' + │ local values │ forced global
restore({mode:'global'}) │ (post-mutation) │ (deliberate commit)

Flow diagram: snapshot lifecycle

Time ──────────────────────────────────────────────────────────►
Request N:
│
├─[1] snap = req.location.snapshot()
│ │ reads root, gzip.level, proxy.readTimeout, …
│ │ via getter (honours read_mode)
│ │ stores copies in NginxSnapshot object
│
├─[2] req.location.root = '/new'
│ │ write_mode='global' → writes directly to shared clcf
│ │ (no per-req snapshot created)
│
├─[3] ← SOMETHING FAILS
│
└─[4] snap.restore()
│ iterates stored fields
│ calls JS_SetPropertyStr(loc_obj, 'root', '/original')
│ → ngx_js_location_set() → need_global=1 → clcf->root = '/original'
│ calls JS_SetPropertyStr(proxy_obj, 'readTimeout', orig_val)
│ → ngx_js_proxy_set_core() → plcf->upstream.read_timeout = orig_val
│
▼
global config is back to what it was at [1]

Flow diagram: local isolation with deliberate commit

Time ──────────────────────────────────────────────────────────►
Request N:
│
├─ setWriteMode('local')
│
├─ snap = req.location.snapshot() ← captures global values
│
├─ req.location.root = '/candidate' ← per-req snapshot created,
│ global unchanged
│
├─ validate() ← test the new config
│ │
│ ├─ OK → commit:
│ │ snap2 = req.location.snapshot() ← captures /candidate
│ │ snap2.restore({ mode: 'global' }) ← writes /candidate → global
│ │
│ └─ FAIL → rollback:
│ snap.restore({ mode: 'local' }) ← reverts local copy
│
│
Request N+1 (concurrent):
│ No write_mode set — reads from global
│ Sees original value UNTIL Request N commits
└─ …

Complete Examples

Example 1: Rollback on Error

Mutate the location config and roll back if the mutation causes a problem.

loc.handler = async (req) => {
const snap = req.location.snapshot();
try {
const cfg = JSON.parse(await req.readBody());
req.location.root = cfg.root;
if (cfg.proxy) {
req.location.proxy.readTimeout = cfg.proxy.readTimeout;
req.location.proxy.connectTimeout = cfg.proxy.connectTimeout;
}
// Test the new config with a probe request
const ok = await probeBackend(req);
if (!ok) {
throw new Error('probe failed');
}
req.json({ applied: true });
} catch (e) {
snap.restore();
req.respond(500, {}, 'Config apply failed: ' + e.message);
}
};

Example 2: Atomic Two-Phase Apply

Validate locally, then commit globally.

loc.handler = async (req) => {
// Phase 1: validate in isolation
req.location.setWriteMode('local');
req.location.setReadMode('local');
const cfg = JSON.parse(await req.readBody());
const orig = req.location.snapshot(); // capture current state
req.location.root = cfg.root;
const valid = await validateConfig(req.location);
if (!valid) {
orig.restore({ mode: 'local' }); // revert local copy
req.respond(400, {}, 'invalid config');
return;
}
// Phase 2: commit validated values globally
const validated = req.location.snapshot(); // capture /local/ values
validated.restore({ mode: 'global' }); // write them to global
req.json({ committed: true });
};

Example 3: Upstream Peer Weight Balancing with Rollback

loc.handler = async (req) => {
const ups = nginx.http.upstreams.find(u => u.name === 'backend');
const snap = ups.snapshot(); // save all peer weights
try {
// Rebalance weights based on health check results
const health = await checkHealth(ups);
ups.peers.forEach((p, i) => {
p.weight = health[i].healthy ? health[i].score : 0;
});
// Verify at least one peer is alive
const alive = ups.peers.some(p => p.weight > 0);
if (!alive) {
throw new Error('all peers down after rebalance');
}
req.json({ rebalanced: true });
} catch (e) {
snap.restore(); // restore original weights
req.respond(503, {}, e.message);
}
};

Example 4: Single-Peer Snapshot for Fine-Grained Rollback

loc.handler = async (req) => {
const ups = nginx.http.upstreams.find(u => u.name === 'backend');
const peer = ups.peers.find(p => p.address === req.getVar('arg_peer'));
if (!peer) {
req.respond(404, {}, 'peer not found');
return;
}
const snap = peer.snapshot(); // snapshot only this peer
peer.down = true; // take peer out of rotation
peer.weight = 0;
// Wait for in-flight requests to drain
await nginx.setTimeout(5000);
const drained = await verifyDrained(peer.address);
if (!drained) {
snap.restore(); // put peer back on failure
req.respond(503, {}, 'drain failed');
return;
}
req.json({ drained: true, peer: peer.address });
};

Example 5: A/B Configuration Experiment

loc.handler = (req) => {
// Route 10% of requests to experimental config
const isExperiment = Math.random() < 0.10;
if (!isExperiment) {
req.sendfile('/index.html');
return;
}
// Local-only mutation — no global side-effect
req.location.setWriteMode('local');
req.location.setReadMode('local');
req.location.root = '/var/www/experiment';
req.location.sendfile = false;
req.location.defaultType = 'text/html; charset=utf-8';
req.sendfile('/index.html');
// local snapshot is automatically discarded when the request ends
};

Example 6: Config Snapshot for Audit

loc.handler = (req) => {
// Return a JSON representation of current location config
const snap = req.location.snapshot();
// NginxSnapshot is opaque — to read its values, read the location directly
const config = {
root: req.location.root,
sendfile: req.location.sendfile,
keepaliveTimeout: req.location.keepaliveTimeout,
proxy: req.location.proxy ? {
readTimeout: req.location.proxy.readTimeout,
connectTimeout: req.location.proxy.connectTimeout,
buffering: req.location.proxy.buffering,
} : null,
};
req.json(config);
};

Example 7: Guarded Global Mutation

Prevent concurrent mutations from interleaving.

let mutationInProgress = false;
loc.handler = async (req) => {
if (mutationInProgress) {
req.respond(429, {}, 'mutation in progress, retry');
return;
}
mutationInProgress = true;
const snap = req.location.snapshot();
try {
const cfg = JSON.parse(await req.readBody());
req.location.root = cfg.root;
req.location.etag = cfg.etag ?? true;
// … more fields …
req.json({ applied: true });
} catch (e) {
snap.restore();
req.respond(500, {}, e.message);
} finally {
mutationInProgress = false;
}
};

API Reference

location.setWriteMode(mode)

Sets the write destination for property assignments on this location and its sub-objects.

Parameter │ Description

mode │ 'global' | 'local' | 'both'

Also propagates the new mode to rctx→write_mode so that sub-object setters (proxy, gzip, etc.) route writes consistently.

location.setReadMode(mode)

Sets the read source for property getters on this location.

Parameter │ Description

mode │ 'global' — always read from global shared struct. 'local' — prefer per-request snapshot; fall back to global.

location.snapshot()

Captures the current readable state of the location and all of its mutable sub-objects.

NginxSnapshot location.snapshot()

Returns a NginxSnapshot object. The snapshot is a point-in-time copy of every settable property value, read through the current read_mode.

Null/undefined property values are silently excluded.

upstream.snapshot()

Captures all peers in the upstream’s current peers[] array.

NginxSnapshot upstream.snapshot()

Each peer becomes a separate node in the snapshot. The snapshot is ordered (peer 0 first, backup peers last).

: If peers are added or removed between snapshot() and restore(), the snapshot nodes point to the original peer objects (which remain valid as long as the upstream zone memory is not recycled). Restoring a snapshot after removePeer() may write to a peer that is no longer in the active list — this is harmless but produces no observable effect.

peer.snapshot() / rrPeer.snapshot()

Captures the five mutable fields of a single peer.

NginxSnapshot peer.snapshot()
NginxSnapshot rrPeer.snapshot()

snap.restore([options])

Re-applies all captured values through the standard setter path.

undefined snap.restore()
undefined snap.restore({ mode: 'global' | 'local' | 'both' })

Option │ Description

mode │ Optional string. When supplied, overrides the current write_mode for the duration of this restore call only. Original mode is restored after all fields are written.

Behaviour:

•

Idempotent — calling restore() multiple times is safe.

•

Best-effort — individual setter errors are silently cleared.

•

Mode override applies to the location node and to rctx→write_mode so sub-object setters also use the requested mode.

•

In config phase (no active request) restore({ mode: 'local' }) is a no-op for sub-objects because there is no per-request context; location core fields are still written to loc_op→write_mode.

nginx.suspendAcceptance()

Removes all listening socket read events from this worker’s event loop. New TCP connections queue in the OS socket backlog; other workers continue accepting normally.

undefined nginx.suspendAcceptance()

Throws TypeError if called outside a worker process. Throws InternalError if the underlying event operation fails.

nginx.resumeAcceptance()

Re-adds the listening socket read events removed by suspendAcceptance(). No-op if acceptance was not suspended.

undefined nginx.resumeAcceptance()

Throws TypeError if called outside a worker process.

: For cross-worker suspension, use nginx.suspendAllWorkers() / nginx.resumeAllWorkers() (documented in the for all workers guide).

NginxSnapshot (opaque object)

NginxSnapshot is an opaque QuickJS object with class name "NginxSnapshot". Its only JS-visible method is restore(). The captured values are not directly accessible from JavaScript.

The snapshot is garbage-collected when the last JS reference to it is dropped; no manual cleanup is required.

Design Notes

Internal snapshot vs JS snapshot

The internal C-level snapshot (ngx_js_ensure_core_snapshot, ngx_js_ensure_module_snapshot) is an automatic mechanism triggered by write_mode='local' setters. It operates at the C struct level and is invisible to JavaScript.

The JS-level snapshot() / restore() operates at the property level: it calls the existing getters and setters. The two mechanisms are complementary:

•

write_mode='local' + internal snapshots → isolation of mutations.

•

snapshot() + restore() → rollback of mutations.

Why restore() is best-effort

Some setters may legitimately fail (e.g. alias on a root-based location throws a type error). Because snapshot() silently skips null/undefined values (and alias returns null for root-based locations), such fields are never captured. The restore() "best-effort" guarantee handles any remaining edge cases — e.g. a location type changed between snapshot and restore — without crashing the request.

Snapshot scope for upstream.snapshot()

upstream.snapshot() captures the current peer array. If peers are added via addPeer() after the snapshot, those new peers are not in the snapshot and will not be removed by restore(). Similarly, if peers are removed via removePeer(), restoring field values to a removed peer has no effect on the live upstream.

For a complete "undo addPeer/removePeer", use the addPeer()/removePeer() methods directly rather than relying on snapshot().